טוב, tov, today's דף daf is ק"ה kuf hey 105, we pick
up at the bottom of ק"ד kuf dalet עמוד ב'. amud bet.
We're dealing with the list of the kings, but we're also trying
to figure out
why certain kings weren't included. That was a whole discussion yesterday, and
then finally the very end of yesterday's דף daf was who did
the counting? It was אנשי כנסת הגדולה. Anshei Knesset HaGedolah. They wanted
to include שלמה Shlomo as a king who didn't have a חלק
לעולם הבא, chelek l'olam haba, and sort of God came out with
a fire from heaven and a heavenly voice, and they wanted to
ignore that heavenly voice, very similar to the whole story of, of
you know, about the תנור של עכנאי, Tanur shel Achnai, but as
opposed to the end of the story of the תנור של עכנאי,
Tanur shel Achnai, which ended with לא בשמים היא, lo bashamayim hi,
we get to decide what the הלכה halacha is, this one ends
with God saying I get to decide who gets to go into
עולם הבא. olam haba. Just because the רבנים rabanim are making up
a list, that's not going to determine who gets into עולם הבא
olam haba or whatever, that's going to be in the end be
my decision, which is a very
like nice sort of like it answered a question, right, which I
think is on our minds, like who told the רבנים rabanim who's
going to get into עולם הבא olam haba or not? They דרשו
darshu it from פסוקים, psukim, but at the end of the day,
like that's their power in terms of הלכה, halacha, but in terms
of these types of questions, ultimately it sort of says God is
saying like that's me for me to decide.
The list is kind of meaningless.
Well, you know, you could, you would say that since God only
came and protested by their desire for שלמה, Shlomo, is it implicitly,
right, it leaves you wondering about that. And so let's pick up
from four lines from the bottom with the punchline of that. יצתה
בת קול ואמרה, yatzta bat kol v'amrah, or a heavenly voice came
out and said המעמך ישלמנה? hame'imcha yishalmena? Will the sort of with
the question of who finds peace, like will that come from you?
Maybe also play with the word שלמה Shlomo here.
Okay, or רש"י Rashi says the word is from the word, not
from שלום Shalom but ישלמנה yishalmena for תשלומין, tashlumin, right? That's obviously,
that's the word. Right. Are you the one who compensates? כי מאסת,
ki ma'asta, you have chosen who to despise. כי אתה תבחר, ki
ata tivchar, do you think you get to choose? ולא אני, v'lo
ani, and I'm not the one who chooses? Okay, then דורשי רשומות,
Dorshei Reshumot, so now that's that list. Now דורשי רשומות, Dorshei Reshumot,
which is those who interpret פסוקים, psukim, always a question of exactly
who this refers to. Anyway היו אומרים, hayu omrim, but these are
people who like would do stuff in אגדתא Aggadata and they said
כולם באים לעולם הבא. kulam ba'im l'olam haba. They took sort of
God's approach one step further. They rejected the whole list. Everybody, even
those wicked kings get עולם הבא. olam haba. שנאמר, she'ne'emar, because based
on the following פסוק: pasuk: לי גלעד ולי מנשה, li Gilead v'li
Menashe, to me is גלעד Gilead and מנשה, Menashe, ואפרים מעוז ראשי,
v'Ephraim ma'oz roshi, אפרים Ephraim is the strength of my head. יהודה
מחוקקי, Yehuda mechokki, יהודה Yehuda is my scepter. מואב סיר רחצי, Moav
sir rachtzi, now those, מואב Moav is the pot in which I
will bathe. אדום
על אדום אשליך נעלי, al Edom ashlich na'ali, on אדום Edom I
will cast my shoes. So obviously the simplest sense of the פסוק
pasuk is like the first half is about God saying I've chosen
the tribes of ישראל Yisrael and I will despise, you know, these
tribes of אדום Edom and מואב Moav and I'll use them to
bathe in and to cast my shoes on. עלי פלשת התרועעי, alai
Pleshet hitro'ai, on me the פלשת, Pleshet, the Philistines will like be
tremble or whatever. So now we're going to interpret it the following
way: לי גלעד ולי מנשה. li Gilead v'li Menashe. So לי גלעד
זה אחאב li Gilead zeh Achav שנפל ברמות גלעד. she'nafal b'ramot Gilead.
That's אחאב Achav who fell in רמות גלעד. Ramot Gilead. He's going
to be with I got him. I you know, as רש"י Rashi
sort of says, it's I will endure his sin, I will carry
his sin. He's going to even he'll get
עולם הבא. olam haba. מנשה כמשמעו. Menashe k'mashma'o. To me is מנשה.
Menashe. מנשה Menashe doesn't mean the tribe of מנשה. Menashe. It means
King מנשה. Menashe. I got him covered too. אפרים מעוז ראשי זה
ירבעם. Ephraim ma'oz roshi zeh Yerovam. That's ירבעם Yerovam because he comes
from אפרים. Ephraim. So he's also I got him covered. יהודה מחוקקי.
Yehuda mechokki. It's very ingenious how they did this, right? יהודה Yehuda
is my scepter. זה אחיתופל. zeh Achitofel. We haven't mentioned אחיתופל Achitofel
yet. Okay, but that's one of the commoners דקאתי מיהודה d'ka'ati mi'Yehuda
who comes from יהודה. Yehuda. מואב סיר רחצי זה גיחזי. Moav sir
rachtzi zeh Geichazi. Oh and now we're getting back to because we're
going through the whole list. We've only been discussing the kings, but
now we're getting onto the commoners which we haven't sort of had
a גמרא Gemara on yet. This is גיחזי Geichazi שלקה עסקי רחיצה
she'laka iskei rechitza that he גיחזי, Geichazi, you know the whole thing
with נעמן Na'aman and he went and whatever so it was all
about the bathing. So that's why that includes that's גיחזי. Geichazi.
על אדום אשליך נעלי זה דואג האדומי. al Edom ashlich na'ali zeh
Doeg HaEdomi. There you go, אדום Edom and אדומי. Edomi. עלי פלשת
התרועעי. alai Pleshet hitro'ai. So what's that? So אמרו מלאכי השרת לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא, amru malachei ha-shareit lifnei ha-kadosh baruch hu, ריבונו של
עולם, ribbono shel olam, אם יבוא דוד שהרג את הפלשתי. im yavo
David she-harag et ha-Plishti. So the פלשת Pleshet is דוד David who
killed the Philistine, who killed, you know, גלית, Goliath, והוריש לבניך גת,
v'horish l'vanecha Gat, and he bequeathed גת Gat to your children. So
מה אתה עושה לו? ma ata oseh lo? What are you going
to do for him? Here you are, you're protecting דואג, Doeg, you
know, who was this person who obviously informed against דוד David to
שאול Shaul and caused all this trouble tragedy. Like what's דוד David
going to say? Okay.
So it says yeah blah blah blah. מה אתה עושה לו? ma
ata oseh lo? אמר להן עלי לעשותן רעים זה לזה. amar lahen
alai la'asotan rei'im zeh la-zeh. Don't worry. עלי התרועעי. alai hitro'ai. I'll
make them friends with one another. You don't worry about it. Okay.
God's though saying like I got it covered. All right? So oh
also אחיתופל, Achitofel, like was- so it was אחיתופל. Achitofel. Two of
these, אחיתופל Achitofel and דואג, Doeg, they're enemies of דוד. Dovid. You're
gonna what are you going to say to דוד? Dovid? God says
I'll make them friends. Okay. So that's a very beautiful דרשה. drasha.
It's a great, very ingenious to get all of them in. Okay.
מדוע שובבה העם הזה ירושלים משובה נצחת. Madua shovevah ha'am hazeh Yerushalayim
meshuvah nitzachat. So why does this people, you know, constantly sort of,
you know, resist God and rebel against God, you know, for an
eternal- how does it translate משובה? meshuvah? Like a resistance or something
or impertinent, rebellion. Okay, so now
persistent rebellion. אמר רב, Amar Rav, so now that we're dealing with
how the kings sinned, right now we're going to talk about the
people. אמר רב, Amar Rav, תשובה נצחת, Teshuvah nitzachat, השיבה כנסת ישראל
לנביא. heshiva Knesses Yisrael l'navi. So this שובבה shovevah we're reading as
a תשובה, teshuvah, not repentance but response. And נצחת, nitzachat, the word
at the end, right, משובה נצחת. meshuvah nitzachat. So the people had,
like, they were- even the people were so sinful and so resistant
to what the נביא navi had to say that they responded to
him with a תשובה נצחת, teshuvah nitzachat, like with a completely devastating
response, like that you couldn't answer it. Okay. אמר
רב, Amar Rav, so what was that? אמר להו לישראל. Amar lehu
l'Yisrael. He said to them, חזרו בתשובה, chizru b'teshuvah, do תשובה. teshuvah.
אבותיכם
שחטאו היכן הם, Avoseichem shechatu heichan heim, your fathers who sinned, where
are they? Look, they're dead. You know? So you don't want to
be like them, so do תשובה. teshuvah. Of course, like, everybody dies,
which is pretty much what they said back to him. אמרו להן,
Amru lahen, they said back to the prophet, ונביאיכם שלא חטאו היכן
הם, Unevieichem shelo chatu heichan heim, how about your friends the נביאים?
nevi'im? They didn't sin, where are they? They're also dead. Everybody dies.
That's not going to get us to do
תשובה. teshuvah. So- היכן הם? Heichan heim? שנאמר, Shenemar, אבותיכם איה הם
והנביאים הלעולם יחיו? Avoseichem ayeih heim vehanevi'im haleolam yichyu? Even the נביאים
nevi'im aren't told forever. אמר להן, Amar lahen, he said to them-
so there's a question. Is he saying אבותיכם חזרו והודו, Avoseichem chazru
vehodu, at least your
fathers did תשובה teshuvah and they admitted? Or is he saying to
them חזרו והודו, chizru vehodu, nevertheless, do תשובה, teshuvah, admit your sin?
שנאמר, Shenemar, as it says, אך דברי וחוקי אשר צויתי את עבדי
הנביאים. Ach devarai vechukai asher tzivisi es avadai hanevi'im. Even my words
that I commanded the prophets נביאים, nevi'im, and the end of the
sort of verse says about how, you know, the people sort of
responded and admitted their sin. So one way of reading this is,
which doesn't fit the idea that it's a completely- that the people
answered a devastating response because then it would just say he told
them to do תשובה, teshuvah, they did תשובה. teshuvah. So the other
way of reading it is your forefathers at least when I gave
them, you know, מוסר, mussar, they did תשובה, teshuvah, you know, you-
you should do the same. Okay. Anyway, there's no sort of end
to that. I mean, there's no, you know, response to that. Now
that doesn't sound so much like a תשובה נצחת, teshuvah nitzachat, you
know, just- but okay. So now it says, but now we're going
to do other versions of what this תשובה נצחת teshuvah nitzachat was.
שמואל אמר, Shmuel amar, באו עשרה בני אדם וישבו לפניו. Bau asara
b'nei adam veyashvu lefanav. Ten people came and sat before the prophet.
Okay. אמר להן, Amar lahen, חזרו בתשובה. chizru b'teshuvah. He said to
them, do תשובה. teshuvah. אמרו לו- Amru lo now this seems to
more like be the strong type of response. עבד שמכרו רבו ואשה
שגרשה בעלה כלום יש לזה על זה כלום? Eved shemachro rabo veishah
shegerashah baalah klum yesh lazeh al zeh klum? After a slave has
been sold by the master or a woman divorced by her husband,
they have nothing to do with one another anymore. If God abandoned
us and God sent us into exile, don't tell us to do
תשובה. teshuvah. That's it. God's abandoned us. We're done. אמר לו הקדוש
ברוך הוא לנביא. Amar lo haKadosh Baruch Hu l'navi. So God said
to the נביא. navi. So that could be certain- you know, sound
like a תשובה נצחת. teshuvah nitzachat. But at the end of the
idea, the תשובה teshuvah isn't נצחת nitzachat because God said to the
נביא. navi. Go tell them- now we're to ישעיהו. Yeshayahu. Before we
were on- you know, we're different נביאים nevi'im here. איזה ספר כריתות
אמכם אשר שלחתיה? Eizeh sefer kerisus imchem asher shillachtiyah? Where is the-
show me your bill of divorce that I sent away- you know,
I sent away your mother. I know. Okay, you're in exile, but
I never divorced you.
או מי מנושי אשר מכרתי אתכם לו? Umi minoshai asher macharti eschem
lo? Who has a creditor that I sold you off to? Okay,
it's never happened. הן בעונותיכם נמכרתם ובפשעיכם שלחה אמכם. Hein baavonoseichem nimkartem
uvifsha'eichem shullechah imchem. Now that's a little bit not saying just like
okay there isn't the divorce but it wasn't me who did it.
You- you did- you got yourself into this position. You sold yourself
off because of your sins. All right. But don't- so- so go
ahead. So I guess the point would be don't blame God. God
wasn't the one who divorced you. You're the one who sent yourself
away and you're the one who can bring yourself back. רב אמר
ריש לקיש, Rav amar Reish Lakish, so that's what ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish says. מאי דכתיב, Mai d'ksiv, what's meant by the verse,
דוד עבדי נבוכדנצר עבדי? Dovid avdi Nevuchadnezzar avdi? So the verse is
always calling דוד Dovid God's servant, but it calls נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar God's
servant. How- what type of comparison is that? So גלוי וידוע לפני
מי שאמר והיה העולם. Galui veyadua lifnei Mi she'amar vehayah haolam. It
was revealed before God, שעתידין ישראל לומר כן, she'asidin Yisrael lomar kein,
that the Jewish people would say what they said to the נביא,
navi, which is like you sold us off, we have no- that's
it, we're done with you. So therefore, what did God do? לפיכך
הקדים הקדוש ברוך הוא וקראו עבדו. Lefichach hikdim haKadosh Baruch Hu vekrao
avdo. Therefore God said- God beat them to the punch and called
נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar His servant or His slave. ועבד שקנה נכסים עבד למי
נכסים למי? V'eved shekanah nechasim eved l'mi nechasim l'mi? And if a
slave buys property, who owns the slave and who owns the property?
The master. So once נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar is God's slave, then when נבוכדנצר
Nevuchadnezzar takes. takes them into captivity, so if Nebuchadnezzar's slaves are also
God's slaves, so you never left being God's servants. You never left
God's servitude. So that's the answer. Okay, so on the one hand,
we're saying it's a תשובה נצחת. Teshuvah nitzachat. It's a completely devastating
response, but then we're saying no, actually, it wasn't... they didn't win
with the response because here was the answer back to them. All
right. One minute. So, okay.
ואף לא רוחכם, Ve-af lo ruchachem, and now also another verse that
directly addresses this. What has... what you have thought to say, היו
לא תהיה, hayoh lo tihyeh, will not be. אשר אתם אומרים נהיה
כגויים כמשפחות הארצות לשרת עץ ואבן. asher atem omrim nihyeh kagoyim kemishpachot
ha'aratzot lisharet etz va-even. You say, "Ah, let's just be like the
גויים. goyim. We'll worship the stones and the wood." חי אני נאום
השם אלוקים. chai ani neum Hashem Elokim. "By my life," says השם
Hashem God, "אם לא ביד חזקה ובזרוע נטויה ובחמה שפוכה אמלוך עליכם.
im lo beyad chazakah uvizroah netuyah uvichemah shefuchah emloch aleichem. Even if
it requires me to come with a powerful hand and with pouring
a fiery anger,
I will be king over you, no matter how much you resist
it. I'm going to take you back as my people and be
king over you." אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, said רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, כה כי האי רתחא לירתח רחמנא עלן. ko ki hai
ritcha lirtach Rachmana alan. Let God be as angry as that on
us, let us suffer all that anger, דלפרקינן, dilfarkinan, as long as
God in the end redeems
us, ולימלוך עליכן. velimloch aleichan. So, it's interesting, before we had the
rabbis that said, "I don't want to live in ימות המשיח yemot
Hamashiach because I don't want to have to suffer
all of the suffering of חבלי משיח," chevlei Mashiach, but here it's
saying, "Okay, God is to express all this anger He will pour
out on us," and רב נחמן Rav Nachman is saying as long
as in the end You redeem us, it's worth it. Charlie wanted
to say something?
Oh, the context of Nebuchadnezzar was...
the prophet was warning that you're going to be conquered by Nebuchadnezzar
and the implication seems to be that Nebuchadnezzar
is acting in God's...
right, correct, correct, but we're making a different דרשה drasha here. Okay.
וייסרו למשפט אלוהיו יורנו. Ve-yisro lamishpat elohav yorenu. Okay,
this is another version of what type of a response the people
gave in resisting the נביא'ס navi's מוסר. mussar. So it says, "They
will sort of subjugate him for justice...
and their God will teach him."
So what does that mean?
אמר רבה בר בר חנה, Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana, אמר להם
נביא לישראל, amar lahem navi l'Yisrael, "חזרו בתשובה, chizru bitshuvah, do תשובה,
teshuvah, חזרו בתשובה." chizru bitshuvah. אמרו לו, Amru lo, they said to
him, "אין אנו יכולים יצר הרע שולט בנו. ein anu yocholim yetzer
hara sholet banu. We can't, we have too big of a יצר
הרע." yetzer hara. אמר להם, Amar lahem, "ייסרו יצריכם, yisru yitzrechem,
take control of your יצר הרע, yetzer hara, subjugate it." אמרו לו,
Amru lo, they said to him, "אלוהיו יורנו, elohav yorenu, let the
person... let the God who created the יצר הרע yetzer hara teach
us how to control our יצר הרע, yetzer hara, then we'll do
it." Okay, so it's a little interesting way of ending the whole
discussion of the kings, why we're sort of fussing about this about
the people, but I guess sort of like saying the people get
the leaders they deserve, yes, and vice versa.
Yes. Maybe this has been mentioned a little bit later, but if
it says that all these people have חלק לעולם הבא, chelek le-olam
haba, does that maybe reflect a position like כל ישראל יש להם
חלק לעולם הבא kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek le-olam haba based on
a position like that?
That these people... well, the כל... kol first of all, as I
said the first day of חלק, chelek. כל ישראל יש להם חלק
לעולם הבא kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek le-olam haba is a line
that was added later to the משנה. Mishnah. It wasn't originally part
of the משנה. Mishnah. Now, there's a whole big article by what's
his name, Orbach, about whether that idea of כל ישראל יש להם
חלק לעולם הבא kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek le-olam haba reflect the
standard approach of חז"ל Chazal or not? Now, so and there's a
good reasonable argument to be made that the dominant approach of חז"ל
Chazal is not that way, like the גמרא Gemara says, צדיקים tzaddikim
get... go to עולם הבא, olam haba, רשעים resha'im go to גיהנום,
Gehinnom, בינונים beinonim or whatever in the middle, so it's not... and
as we've been discussing, it's one thing to say you're resurrected in
תחיית המתים techiyat hameitim and you're judged, but that you actually have
a portion in the world to come no matter how big of
a רשע rasha you are, that's from the one hand. On the
other hand, the very fact that the משנה Mishnah itself mentions a
small number of really wicked people that don't have a חלק לעולם
הבא, chelek le-olam haba, the message is pretty implicit that everybody else
does have it. And yes, and the approach here that sort of
says even these four have it is taking it even to the
furthest extreme, no matter that even the most wicked of ישראל, Yisrael,
right, so it's definitely... but everybody is within the assumption that the
standard is that everybody has a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek le-olam haba.
The question is, are there any exceptions? Are even the worst kings
going to be the exceptions to that?
And that opinion that said these people, do they also mean the
הדיוטות hedyotot or just the kings?
No, they listed the הדיוטות hedyotot also, the דרשה drasha listed the
הדיוטות. hedyotot. We haven't discussed the הדיוטות hedyotot yet, but the דרשה
drasha did.
Yeah, from, you
know, at the end of the day, it doesn't list בלעם. Bilaam.
The four הדיוטות hedyotot and בלעם Bilaam is the non-Jew. So it
listed the three Jews. We're about to get to it, right? ארבעה
הדיוטות בלעם דואג אחיתופל וגיחזי. arbaah hedyotot Bilaam Doeg Achitofel ve-Geichazi. So
the דרשה drasha we just did that they all have חלק לעולם
הבא chelek le-olam haba mentioned דואג, Doeg, אחיתופל, Achitofel, and גיחזי, Geichazi,
but בלעם, Bilaam, right, because that's still the כל ישראל יש להם
חלק לעולם הבא. kol Yisrael yesh lahem chelek le-olam haba. By the
non-Jews, you have to be חסידי אומות העולם. chassidei umot ha-olam. And
that's the contrast, and that's actually what we're about to get to.
Like by the Jews, even whether you hold by that list or
not, it's only a tiny number. Even normal רשעים resha'im do have
a חלק לעולם הבא chelek le-olam haba if the... is the point
of the משנה, Mishnah, right? But by the non-Jews, it's only the
חסידי אומות העולם, chassidei umot ha-olam, so there's still a different standard
of who gets to enter in. Yeah.
Well, if only the חסידי אומות העולם, chassidei umot ha-olam, we didn't
need to say that בלעם Bilaam doesn't have...
Yeah, it's an interesting point. We'll get to that. We're about to
turn to that in a minute. Let's...
You know at the end of the day yesterday we started saying
that there was a בת קול bat kol that says I decide
who's חלק. So then what was our whole discussion if that's if
that's where we ended it? We didn't really need to have this
whole discussion that this person didn't you know how come because of
his son whatever. No because God decides who it is.
Alright, alright, because at the end of the day so we said
like it's not clear what the message is at the end of
that. Is the message that like none of this none of this
matters, it's all for God to decide, or it's like don't tell
me you're leaving you're putting שלמה Shlomo on the list, I'm gonna
put my foot down here. You know so it's an interesting it's
not clear exactly what the message is. Anyway let's go on. You
don't get to ask those questions when you come late. ארבעה הדיוטות
arba'ah hedyotot בלעם Bilam דואג Doeg אחיתופל Achitophel וגיחזי. v'Geichazi. בלעם Bilam
so now we're gonna do a דרשה drasha on their names again
like we did before. בלא עם b'lo am without a nation. Okay
בלק Balak well that was we're getting to that. דבר אחר davar
acher בלעם Bilam שבלע she-bala wiped out עם. am. Okay בן בעור
Ben Be'or
because you don't know where בלעם Bilam comes from right exactly? It
says he sent to בלעם Bilam ארץ בני עמו Eretz Bnei Ammo
whose nation? בלעם's Bilam nation? You know בלק's Balak nation? Anyway בן
בעור Ben Be'or שבא על בעיר she-ba al be'ir that he either
he or his father, not exactly fair this דרשה, drasha, we're gonna
get it later explicitly with בלעם, Bilam,
had intercourse with his animal, okay with his well with בלעם Bilam
it's gonna be with his donkey. תנו tanu הוא בעור hu Be'or
his father's name was בעור Be'or same person as בעור Be'or הוא
כושן רשעתים. hu Cushan-Rishathaim. You gotta love that name. Rishaim? I what
can you what do you want me to tell you? הוא לבן
הארמי. hu Lavan Ha-Arami. Okay so this guy lived a long time,
okay. It was לבן Lavan way back in the from the time
of יעקב, Yaakov, you know this other guy this כושן רשעתים Cushan-Rishathaim
that gave the Jewish people a hard time you know later in
the time of the when they entered into the land, right exactly
בלעם Bilam these are all the same person. Okay so בעור Be'or
ש... now why does he have multiple names? בעור Be'or שבא על
בעיר. He he had intercourse with his animal.
כושן רשעתים דעבד שתי רשעיות בישראל Cushan-Rishathaim d'avad shtei rishaos b'Yisrael he
did these two evil things to ישראל. Yisrael. אחת בימי יעקב achas
bimei Yaakov since we're saying he's also לבן Lavan so he tried
to wipe out you know יעקב Yaakov which would have ended the
Jewish people. ואחת בימי שופטים v'achas bimei Shofetim and one of the
times of the שופטים Shofetim right? And so then three times actually
if you count the time of what's בלעם Bilam and בלק. Balak.
Well actually no that would this is his father, בלעם. Bilam. Okay
so father twice tried to wipe out you know the Jewish people.
ומה שמו u-ma shemo what's his name? לבן הארמי שמו. Lavan Ha-Arami
shemo. I don't know what the point is about tying these particular
people together. I mean they were non-Jews who tried to hurt the
Jewish people or whatever I mean so maybe you want to sort
of associate בלעם Bilam with his father came from a similar type
of a family. But anyway moving
on. Okay
where
were we? Okay. כתיב בן בעור וכתיב בנו בעור. kesiv Ben Be'or
v'kesiv b'no Be'or. One פסוק pasuk says the son of בעור Be'or
and the other says בנו b'no which could just be poetic but
they're reading it here בנו בעור b'no Be'or meaning not the son
of בעור Be'or but בעור Be'or is his son. Okay so what
does this mean? אמר רבי יוחנן אביו בנו היה לו בנביאות. amar
Rabbi Yochanan aviv b'no haya lo binvi'ut. His בעור Be'or is his
son means when it comes to greatness in prophecy בעור was second
to בלעם. Bilam. His father was his quote unquote son, his junior
in matters of prophecy. Okay now now the גמרא Gemara gets to
the bigger point. בלעם הוא דלא אתי לעלמא דאתי Bilam hu d'lo
asi l'alma d'asi so בלעם Bilam doesn't get a portion in the
world to come. הא אחריני אתו ha achrini asu means sounds like
other non-Jews have a portion in the world to come what other
non-Jews have a portion in the world to come. מתניתין מני היא
masnisin manni hi who's our משנה? mishna? רבי יהושע היא. Rabbi Yehoshua
hi. It's רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua דתניא d'tanya which we learned in
a ברייתא braita רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer ישובו רשעים לשאולה
yashuvu reshaim l'she'olah the wicked will go down into the you know
the nether world or whatever to the depths. כל גוים שכחי אלהים
kol goyim shichechei elohim all the nations those who forget God. So
ישובו רשעים לשאולה yashuvu reshaim l'she'olah אלו פושעי ישראל eleh poshei Yisrael
the sinners of ישראל. Yisrael. Now by the way notice that now
it's not just four people that go into don't get עולם הבא.
olam haba. It's all the רשעים resha'im which is the standard I
would say theology.
Anyway כל גוים שכחי אלהים kol goyim shichechei elohim אלו פושעי עובדי
כוכבים דברי רבי אליעזר eleh poshei ovdei kochavim divrei Rabbi Eliezer the
sinners of the non-Jews. Now that's a little bit strange. That makes
it sound like the text here is a little is a little
not clear because that makes it sound like he's saying if you're
a sinful non-Jew right the same parallels exactly פושעי ישראל poshei Yisrael
פושעי עובדי כוכבים. poshei ovdei kochavim. But his real דרשה drasha is
to make is to read the verse as an equality and not
as a not equality whatever like as an identity. Right כל גוים
שכחי אלהים. kol goyim shichechei elohim. By definition all the nations are
are defined as those who forget God. So even not רשעי גוים
rishai goyim all the גוים goyim are by definition defined as רשעים.
resha'im. Okay that's really now this is in the תוספתא Tosefta it's
much longer in the תוספתא Tosefta than it is here and it's
clearer in the תוספתא Tosefta than it is here. So his basic
דרשה drasha is כל all the nations are considered
שכחי אלהים. shichechei elohim. אמר לו
רבי יהושע
amar lo
Rabbi Yehoshua the רשעים resha'im it's only
ישראל Yisrael only the רשעים. resha'im. אמר לו רבי יהושע וכי נאמר
בכל גוים amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua v'chi ne'emar b'chol goyim not exactly
also clear in this version. What's his response? Does it say amongst
the nations? והלא לא נאמר אלא כל גוים שכחי אלהים v'halo lo
ne'emar ela kol goyim shichechei elohim again not exactly clear the grammatical
point. He’s making but the upshot is clear. אלא ישובו רשעים לשאולה,
מני הוא? Ela yashuvu reshaim lish'olah, mani hu? Who are the רשעים?
reshaim? כל גוים שוכחי אלוהים, kol goyim shochechei Elohim, those who are
from the nations forget God, those are the רשעים. reshaim. Okay, so
again, it's really like this is not clear at all how they're
arguing. I mean, you sort of see whether they're arguing do you
read it all those of the nations who forget God or do
you read it all the nations forget God? That's clearly what the
דרשה drasha is. But the very way the גמרא Gemara has it,
it's very unclear right how
to read.
Yes, I did not get a chance to get the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
to the point, we were just so much in this part of
it, I did not, but I will tell you the תוספתא, Tosefta,
okay. You want to hear the תוספתא? Tosefta? First of all, the
תוספתא Tosefta starts interesting. First of all, the beginning of the תוספתא,
Tosefta, פרק יג, Perek yud-gimmel, is: תנא בני רשעי ישראל אין להם
חלק לעולם הבא. Tanna: Bnei rish'ei Yisrael ein lahem chelek l'olam haba.
Bnei what? The sons of the רשעים, reshaim, שנאמר, shene'emar, כי, ki,
that doesn't sound so fair. הנה יום בא בוער כתנור, Hinei yom
ba bo'er katanur, דברי רבן גמליאל. divrei Rabban Gamliel. רבי יהושע אומר
באין הן לעולם הבא. Rabbi Yehoshua omer: bo'in hen l'olam haba. Okay.
This is פרק יג הלכה א, Perek yud-gimmel, Halacha aleph, well, it's
whatever in the תוספתא. Tosefta. No, they do get עולם הבא. olam
haba. רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is very inclusive. Okay. And now this
actually is very relevant because it's assuming that they also are רשעים,
reshaim, the בני רשעי ישראל, bnei rish'ei Yisrael, but they're רשעים reshaim
because they were raised that way. They were raised like it's a
whole question of תינוק שנשבה. tinok shenishba. Yeah. So if you look
at it, he continues and he says, ולהלן הוא אומר שומר פתאים
השם, ulahalan hu omer: shomer peta'im Hashem, ולהלן הוא אומר גדו אילנא
וקציצו ענפוהי ברם עיקר שרשוהי בארעא שבוקו. v'lahalan hu omer: godu ilana
v'katzitzu anpohi beram ikar shoreshohi b'ara shevoku. So two things. Number one
is שומר פתאים השם. shomer peta'im Hashem. It's not their fault they're
פתאים, peta'im, they've been misled. Okay. And number two is quoting a
verse from Daniel, cut down the tree and leave the roots, okay,
which is that even if you punish the father, like maybe something
good will come out of the children. So that's a fascinating discussion
about people who are wicked, but because they were raised in those
types of families. So that's question number one. Okay. אמר רבן גמליאל
אני מקיים, Amar Rabban Gamliel: ani mekayem, okay, da da da. Now,
next part. Okay. רבי אליעזר
אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, כל רשעי, kol rish'ei, so first it says,
רשעי עובדי כוכבים לא חיים ולא נידונים. rish'ei ovdei kochavim lo chayin
v'lo nidonim. בני רשעי עובדי כוכבים לא חיים ולא נידונים? Bnei rish'ei
ovdei kochavim lo chayin v'lo nidonim? I'm sorry.
בני רשעי עובדי כוכבים לא חיים ולא נידונים. Bnei rish'ei ovdei kochavim
lo chayin v'lo nidonim. Thank you. Okay, that's ending the issue about
the children.
Now, רבי אליעזר אומר כל רשעי עובדי כוכבים אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא שנאמר ישובו רשעים לשאולה כל גוים שוכחי אלוהים ישובו רשעים לשאולה
אלו רשעי ישראל כל גוים שוכחי אלוהים אלו רשעי עובדי כוכבים Rabbi
Eliezer omer: Kol rish'ei ovdei kochavim ein lahem chelek l'olam haba shene'emar:
yashuvu reshaim lish'olah kol goyim shochechei Elohim. Yashuvu reshaim lish'olah, elu rish'ei
Yisrael. Kol goyim shochechei Elohim, elu rish'ei ovdei kochavim. אמר לו רבי
יהושע אילו אמר הכתוב, Amar lo Rabbi Yehoshua: Ilu amar hakatuv, here
it's a lot clearer. Had the verse said, ישובו רשעים לשאולה כל
גוים ושתק היה
אומר כדבריך. yashuvu reshaim lish'olah kol goyim v'shatak haya omer kidvarecha. If
it said that the wicked go down to the depths all of
the nations, period, you'd be right. It means all the nations are
being viewed of as wicked. Okay.
היה אומר כדבריך. Haya omer kidvarecha. Where
are we? אלו רשעי ישראל ורשעי עובדי כוכבים עכשיו שאמר הכתוב שוכחי
אלוהים, Elu rish'ei Yisrael v'rish'ei ovdei kochavim. Achshav she'amar hakatuv 'shochechei Elohim',
only those who forget God, הא יש צדיקים בעובדי כוכבים שיש להם
חלק לעולם הבא. ha yesh tzaddikim b'ovdei kochavim sheyesh lahem chelek l'olam
haba. There are צדיקים tzaddikim that do have a portion in the
world to come. Okay, so it's clearer what they're debating. Right, do
you read it as an identity? All the nations are considered שוכחי
אלוהים, shochechei Elohim, all the nations by definition are רשעים, reshaim, or
those among them who are שוכחי אלוהים, shochechei Elohim, they don't get
חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. Okay. And again, רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua is a much more
inclusive attitude towards עולם הבא. olam haba. And you might also remember
that there's a debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua about whether we need to do תשובה teshuva in order
for God to like bring the משיח. Mashiach. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer said if you don't do תשובה, teshuva, משיח's Mashiach never going
to come. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said God will force us
to do תשובה, teshuva, like משיח Mashiach is going to come regardless.
Okay. So רבי יהושע's Rabbi Yehoshua a much more sort of welcoming
type of approach.
So he says that רשעים reshaim of the עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
don't have a חלק לעולם הבא. chelek l'olam haba. He says that
still you may still assume that by default all עובדי כוכבים ovdei
kochavim are not רשעים, reshaim, but he still says... Right, you could
have said...
right,
what about all the בינונים beinonim of the עובדי כוכבים? ovdei kochavim?
I understand. Anyway, so this is the fascinating debate and I should
say that, you know, this is I think a, you know, of
all the like there's so many separate but all this is like
has huge theological like implications. I mean, on the one hand Michael's
correct, first of all it doesn't address the בינונים. beinonim. The fact
that the משנה Mishnah says בלעם Bilam doesn't have a חלק לעולם
הבא chelek l'olam haba would actually make it sound even like a
broader statement than רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, right, that unless you're really,
really wicked, you know, maybe there's a slight difference. Like maybe we'll
say the really wicked even if you're ישראל, Yisrael, then even if
you're really wicked you get in, but by a non-Jew a wicked
person, a really wicked person doesn't. Okay. But nevertheless it still sounds
like it's pretty broad acceptance. But anyway, so first of all there's
a question like how do we פסקן? pasken? I mean, do you
פסקן pasken theology? Like we just started the whole idea, you know,
God says it's up for me to decide. So you can't really
פסקן pasken theology, but nevertheless רמב״ם Rambam says, you know, that חסידי
אומות העולם יש להם חלק לעולם הבא. chasidei umot ha'olam yesh lahem
chelek l'olam haba. And in a way it makes a lot of
sense because if we believe... believe, like we learned earlier in this
מסכתא, masechta, there are like שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvos b'nei
Noach, right? So I think like it's amazing, you know, with all
the claims that Judaism is like, you know, I don't know, I
don't know, racist but like ethnic or you know, elitist, whatever, it's
like the chosen nation. So besides that we accept, you know, conversion
like every other sort of religion accepts conversion, but as far as
I know, even with all our idea of chosen nation, we're the
only religion, I mean tell me of another religion, Charlie maybe you
know, that actually says that you don't have to be a member
of that faith and you actually and you can still have like
achieve salvation, right, and you can still actually like there's there's a
divine plan, you know, and a way of people to live a
life serving God without being members of the faith. Like I have
no idea of any other religion that says that. But we have
that, right? We have שבע מצוות בני נח. sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach.
Okay, so that's point number one. Now, of course it would how
do you deal with it if you say there's שבע מצוות בני
נח sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach and then
they don't have a חלק עולם הבא? cheilek olam haba? So does
that mean like okay God has given them something to do
and God
will
reward
or punish them
in this world? Or maybe there'll be some other worldly reward,
but it won't be עולם הבא? olam haba? Like it seems like
if you're having שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach, you
know, and your whole system of reward and punishment is ultimately an
עולם הבא olam haba system fundamentally, right, that's sort of, you know,
where we are. So it would seem like you have to link
that with the idea of חסידי אומות העולם יש להם חלק לעולם
הבא. Chasidei Umos Ha'olam yeish lahem cheilek l'olam haba. I really don't
know how like the רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer idea works together with
the idea of שבע מצוות בני נח, sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach, but
certainly רמב״ם, Rambam, you know, sort of rules, again I don't know
what it means to rule, but rules that, you know, like רבי
יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua that they have a portion in the world to
come. It's actually interesting, you know, that some of the אחרונים acharonim
or whatever, נושאי כלים nosei keilim of the רמב״ם Rambam in general,
like they didn't like the idea, you know, it's sort of like
the idea like everybody has their different path up the mountain, like
our path is the תרי״ג מצוות, taryag mitzvos, their path is the
שבע מצוות, sheva mitzvos, but they also get a portion in the
world to come? But then you can understand some people feeling like,
wait a minute, but we got it a lot harder than they
did. We have to do all these מצוות, mitzvos, they only have
the שבע מצוות, sheva mitzvos, like is that fair that they do
less and they still have a portion in the world and they
have an equal portion? So if you like look at the רדב״ז
Radbaz who's one of the commentators on the רמב״ם, Rambam, classic commentator,
he basically says, 'Alright, they have a portion in the world to
come, but they don't it's not as good as our portion,' you
know. So it's interesting to find these areas of difference, like, you
know, and maybe like again as we've been saying, only the חסידים
Chasidim get a חלק עולם הבא. cheilek olam haba. Anyway, but it's
still such a really important statement in terms of, you know, you
don't have to be Jewish in order to merit עולם הבא. olam
haba. Yes.
Does רמב״ם Rambam say that they have to keep the שבע מצוות
בני נח sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach to be a צדיק? tzaddik?
Yes. Well, it's there's a very interesting רמב״ם Rambam I spoke about
that last שבת Shabbos or whatever. רמב״ם Rambam says if you keep
the שבע מצוות בני נח sheva mitzvos b'nei Noach and you not
only just says you have to keep them, says and you do
them because you believe that God commanded them, then הרי זה מחסידי
אומות העולם ויש לו חלק לעולם הבא. harei zeh m'chasidei umos ha'olam
v'yeish lo cheilek l'olam haba. But he says if somebody keeps them
out of their own judgment and not and does not not because
of a belief that God commanded them through משה, Moshe, then it
says אינו מחסידי אומות העולם. eino m'chasidei umos ha'olam. And here's one
of the biggest theological גרסאות girsaos questions. So some have אינו מחסידי
אומות העולם eino m'chasidei umos ha'olam and argue it is ולא מחכמיהם—he's
v'lo m'chachameihem not of the pious of the nations of the world
and not of their wise men. And others have the גרסא, girsa,
instead of a ו, vov, ולא מחכמיהם, v'lo m'chachameihem, they have an
א, aleph, אלא מחכמיהם. ela m'chachameihem. He's not pious, but he's wise.
Right, because piety specifically has to do with a relationship to God
and so on. And he doesn't explicitly say that they don't have
a חלק לעולם הבא cheilek l'olam haba if they keep them out
of their own judgment. It's sort of implies it, but it's not
explicit. Anyway, it's a much longer discussion. Back to the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes.
So if aren't we still imposing? You were saying that no other
religion might allow others who are not in their religion to receive
salvation. Right. But here with the שבע מצוות, sheva mitzvos, we're still
imposing that?
Right, but that's always true. Like if I say, yeah, but if
I have a religion, I say, well, you don't have to be
whatever, Buddhist, Christian, or whatever, to receive salvation, I would still say,
but you have to do x, y, and
z, right? I'm not just going to say you can go ahead
and be an immoral person and receive salvation. My religion still might
teach me that you might still have to live a righteous life,
right? You're so... so you're right, meaning we're still sort of dictating
the terms of it, but we're not saying that you have to
be Jewish. Okay, but but still to me that's a חידוש, chiddush,
right? Do you... do any Christian sects believe that somebody could be
not Christian and live a righteous life and get salvation or not
Muslim and live a righteous life? Charlie, what do you say?
There are some Christian sects that do, but they're considered heretical.
There you
go, exactly.
Alright, כבני רשע, kivnei rasha, you know, that's the standard thing of
אומות העולם umos ha'olam and עובדי עבודה זרה? ovdei avodah zarah?
No, no, no, that was assuming they were wicked and even so.
Alright, so now we continue. Alright, we're continuing. Okay. ואף הוא היה
באותה עצה—back v'af hu hayah b'osah eitzah to בלעם. Bilaam. So now
getting back to the discussion. Now back to בלעם, Billam, so now
getting back to the discussion specifically about בלעם. Billam. ואף אותו רשע
נתן סימן בעצמו. Ve'af oso rasha nasan siman be'atzmo. Even that רשע
rasha בלעם Billam gave a sign to know whether he would get
a חלק לעולם הבא. cheilek l'olam habah. תמות נפשי מות ישרים ותהי
אחריתי כמהו. Tamus nafshi mos yesharim vetehi achrisi komohu. If תמות נפשי
מות ישרים, Tamus nafshi mos yesharim, if I die like the righteous
die, ותהי אחריתי כמהו, tehi achrisi komohu, you know that I will
have a similar end and I'll get עולם הבא. Olam habah. ואם
לאו, Ve'im lav, and if I don't have a peaceful end, because
he died in the battle with ישראל Yisrael and so on, then
הנני הולך לעמי, hineni holeich l'ami,
I'm sorry, did I skip a line? No.
הנני הולך לעמי, Hineni holeich l'ami, I'll go where my nation goes,
I won't get עולם הבא. Olam habah.
That means, you know, the standard might be that they don't get
עולם הבא.
Olam habah. I understand. וילכו זקני מואב וזקני מדין. Vayelchu ziknei Moav
veziknei Midyan. So the elders of מואב Moav and the elders of
מדין Midyan went. Now we're going to do the whole story with
בלעם Billam to get him to come. תנא מדין ומואב לא היה
להם שלום מעולם. Tana Midyan uMoav lo hayah lahem shalom me'olam. They
never, they were two nations that were constantly at war. And nevertheless
they made peace in order because they had a common enemy, because
they were afraid of
ישראל Yisrael here. משל לשני כלבים שהיו בעדר. Mashal lishnei kelavim shehayu
be'eder. There were two dogs that were in a flock. Interesting, this
speaks about like these sheepdogs. Why specifically dogs in a flock? Anyway,
והיו צהובים זה לזה, vehayu tzehubim zeh lazeh, and they were sort
of like, you know, enraged in one another. Their faces were like,
you know, I don't know, like lit up against one another. בא
זאב ובא על האחד. Ba ze'ev uva al ha'echad. Because here it
is, I guess you're right, because like here's like a wolf is
coming and it's going to attack the flock,
על האחד. Al ha'echad. אמר האחד אם איני עוזרו, Amar ha'echad im
eini ozro, if I don't help my, this dog who's my enemy,
this fellow dog here, היום הורג אותו, hayom horeig oso, today the
wolf will kill him, ולמחר בא עלי, ulmachar ba alai, and tomorrow
he'll kill me. I guess it's why the wolf is attacking because
he wants to get to the sheep. הלכו שניהם והרגו את הזאב.
Halchu sheneihem vehargu es haze'ev. So they teamed up to kill the
זאב. ze'ev. So here too, I guess it's, you know, בלק Balak
is protecting his flock of the people of מואב, Moav, and they're
joining together with the leaders of מדין Midyan to protect their flock
as well because they see ישראל Yisrael as the threat. What's that
word about strange bedfellows? What's that line? Politics makes strange bedfellows.
There
is some other line about a common enemy, right? Whatever. Anyway, אמר
רב פפא היינו דאמרי אינשי, Amar Rav Pappa hainu de'amrei inshi, that's
what people say, כרכושתא ושונרא, karkushta veshunra, like the weasel and the
cat, which are like sworn enemies, עבדו הלולא מתרבא דביש גדא. avdu
hilula mitarba devish gada. They made a feast from the fat of
a bad, like of an enemy that suffered a bad luck. So,
whatever. Anyway, so common enemies brings other people, brings other enemies together.
A common cause or common enemy. וישבו שרי מואב עם בלעם. Vayeshu
srei Moav im Billam. So now the officers of מואב Moav stayed
with בלעם Billam to see what God would say. ושרי מדין להיכן
אזלו? Vesrei Midyan leheichan azlu? So where did the officers of מדין
Midyan go?
כיון דאמר להו לינו פה הלילה והשיבותי אתכם דבר, Keivan de'amar lehu
linu poh halailah vehashivosi eschem davar, stay over tonight, let me tell
you what God's going to say to me. אמרו כלום יש אב
ששונא את בנו? Amru klum yesh av shesonei es bno? Why, he
wants God to curse his people? So here it obviously has it
like that they recognized, you know, that God is the God of
the Jewish people. Even from an idolatrous perspective and they might think
every nation has its God,
if they thought that בלעם Billam needed permission from the God of
ישראל, Yisrael, then he said, well, that ain't going to happen, so
they just gave up on him. אמר רב נחמן חוצפא אפילו כלפי
שמיא מהני. Amar Rav Nachman chutzpah afilu klapei shamaya mahani. If you're
acting like with חוצפא, chutzpah, with temerity or whatever, it'll get you,
you know, it'll not necessarily it's the right way to act, but
it'll get you places. Even vis-à-vis God.
שמעיקרא כתיב לא תלך עמהם. Sheme'ikara kesiv lo teleich imahem. First God
says don't go with them. ולבסוף כתיב קום לך אתם. ulvasof kesiv
kum leich itam. And then he kept on nudging God and had
the חוצפא chutzpah to act against. And God finally gave in. רש"י
Rashi said it was the חוצפא chutzpah that he had to the
שרי מואב srei Moav and the מדין Midyan which was, but I
don't think that, רש"י Rashi says לינו פה, linu poh,
שמה יאמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא בתחילה לא תלך. shema yomar lo
hakadosh baruch hu betchilah lo seleich. I don't know why it was
חוצפא chutzpah that he said to them stay over another night or
something. To me it was חוצפא chutzpah that he decided that he
thought like he could ask God after God had already told him
no.
אמר רב ששת חוצפא מלכותא בלא תאגא. Amar Rav Sheshes chutzpah malchusa
bela taga. Speaking of חוצפא, chutzpah, if you're able to sort of
be
like temerity, I think is the word, but anyway, you know, a
little brazen or whatever, then that could give you power like it's
a king without a crown. It's not recognized power, it's informal power.
If you're a pushy brazen חוצפא chutzpah person, you're able to wield
power beyond the office that you have officially recognized. But you know
that like at weddings, there could be some guy that doesn't have
a standing in the company or whatever, but because he's like such
a נודניק nudnik and a חוצפא chutzpah or whatever, he manages to
get his way. It's a very powerful like idea like it's kingship
without the
crown. דכתיב, Dechesiv, because דוד Dovid says ואנכי היום רך ומשוח מלך
והאנשים האלה בני צרויה קשים ממני. va'anochi hayom rach umishuach melech veha'anashim
ha'eleh bnei Tzeruyah kashim mimeni. So this is why דוד Dovid didn't
take vengeance from the sons of צרויה Tzeruyah who were like attacked
members and whatever, you know, in דוד'ס Dovid's sort of... officers or
whatever, because he basically said, look, I'm just a young king and
they're more powerful than me. Okay, they had shown this, you know,
this sort of arrogance and temerity and they acted in this way,
like he was a little bit afraid of them, you know, even
though he was the king. Okay. רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, בלעם Bilam
חיגא ברגלו
אחת היה. chiga b'raglo achas haya. He was lame in one leg.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, וילך שפי. vayelech shefi. He went שפי shefi and somehow
שפי shefi means like רש״י Rashi says it's like it means displaced,
like one leg was displaced from its place,
dislocated. וילך שפי. Vayelech shefi. שמשון Shimshon בשתי רגליו, bishtei raglav, שמשון
Shimshon in two of legs, which is pretty amazing considering what who
שמשון Shimshon was. שנאמר, Shene'emar, שפיפון עלי אורח. shefiffon alei orach. This
is about a descendant of דן Dan that's identified with שמשון Shimshon
who was like a serpent, but the double language of שפיפון shefiffon
means that even that he had like some type of a lameness
in both legs. הנושך עקבי סוס. Hanoshech ikvei sus. Okay. בלעם Bilam
סומא באחת מעיניו היה. suma b'achas me'einav haya. He also was blind
in one eye. שנאמר, Shene'emar, שתום העין. sh'sum ha'ayin. Now שתום העין
sh'sum ha'ayin presumably the easiest way to read it is like סתום,
satum, closed. But רש״י Rashi reads it, then he wouldn't be saying
about himself, רש״י Rashi reads the word שתום sh'sum to somehow mean
open in one eye. Don't ask me. But anyway, but if you're
open in one eye, it means implicitly you're closed in the other.
Okay. קוסם באמתו היה. Kosem b'amato haya. Not only that, he was
a phallo-focused... I don't know what to tell you about that. I
know, I know. I don't know what to tell you about that.
קוסם באמתו היה. Kosem b'amato haya. He would deal necromancy with his
penis. דכתיב הכא, D'chsiv hacha, נופל וגלוי עיניים. nofel v'galui einayim. וכתיב
התם, U'chsiv hatam, falling down and open eyes. הנה המן נופל על
המיטה אשר אסתר עליה. Hineh Haman nofel al hamitta asher Ester aleha.
So the falling there had to do with sexual matters, so here
too. אתמר מר זוטרא אמר, Itmar Mar Zutra amar, קוסם באמתו היה.
kosem b'amato haya. מר בריה דרבינא אמר, Mar berei d'Ravina amar, שבא
על אתונו. sheba al atono. No, the idea of falling down, which
clearly has sexual connotations, it means not about how he did his
necromancy or whatever, but it means that he actually had intercourse with
his donkey. מאן דאמר קוסם באמתו היה כדאמרן. Man d'amar kosem b'amato
haya k'damaran. מאן דאמר בא על אתונו, Man d'amar ba al atono,
like we said, by this first by אסתר. Ester. כתיב הכא, Ksiv
hacha, כרע שכב כארי, kara shachav k'ari,
crouches down, lies down like a lion. That's part of בלעם'ס Bilam's
prophecy. וכתיב התם, U'chsiv hatam, and it says there by יעל Yael
and
סיסרא, Sisra, בין רגליה כרע נפל שכב. bein ragleha kara nafal shachav.
Between her, you know, her legs he fell down, which there clearly
has sexual imagery. So there too, here too it had a sexual
implication.
This is his donkey as opposed to anyone else.
Well, we're going to get to that. Okay, because he has a
very... he has a very intimate relationship with his donkey, as we're
about to see. ויודע דעת עליון. V'yodea da'as elyon. Now in describing
himself he says, the one who knows the thoughts of the Most
High. This is a great line in the גמרא. Gemara. השתא דעת
בהמתו לא הוה ידע, Hashta da'as behemto lo hava yada, דעת עליון
הוה ידע? da'as elyon hava yada? He didn't know what his own
animal was thinking, he knows what God is thinking? Now, you presumably
that means because his animal could see the angel and he couldn't
see the angel. But the גמרא Gemara is going to use this
to tell a different story, not so much he didn't know what
his animal was thinking, but he wasn't even as smart as his
animal. His animal bested him in an argument. Okay. His beast bested
him. Okay. מאי דעת בהמתו, Mai da'as behemto, what does that mean?
דאמרי ליה, D'amri leh, מאי טעמא לא רכבת אסוסיא, mai ta'ama lo
rachavt asusia, because
the שרי מואב sarei Moav said to him, hey, why are you
on a donkey? Why aren't you on a horse? Like, that's like
a more כבודיק kavodik way of riding. אמר להו, Amar lehu, דשדי
להו ברטיבא. d'shadei lehu birtiva. Nah,
it's better because, you know, the donkey eats this like grass in
the swamp stuff so it's easier, I don't have to worry about
feeding it so much. אמרה ליה, Amra leh, so the donkey said
to him, הלא אנכי אתונך? halo anochi asonecha? What are you talking
about? Like, oh, you're using me because it's easier like today ad
hoc. No, I'm your donkey, you're always use me. אמר לה, Amar
lah, לטעינה בעלמא. l'te'ina b'alma. Nah, I only use you when I
have a burden to carry. So she says, no, אשר רכבת עלי.
asher rachavta alai. No, I'm your donkey that you ride on regularly,
don't make it seem like this is some chance thing. אמר לה,
Amar lah, אקראי בעלמא. akrai b'alma. Ah, only every now and then.
No, מעודך עד היום הזה. me'odecha ad hayom hazeh.
No, you're always riding on me. ולא עוד אלא, V'lo od ela,
not only that am I your... you know, your constant way in
which you ride, okay, and you're trying to be dismissive of it,
אלא שאני עושה לך מעשה אישות בלילה. ela she'ani osa lach ma'aseh
ishus balayla. I act as your wife at night. כתיב הכא, Ksiv
hacha, ההסכן הסכנתי, hahasken haskanti, לעשות לך כה. la'asot lach koh. Have
I ever endangered or whatever to act this way to you? So
the word סכן saken here is being read not as like סכנה
sakana or something like that, or thoughts or whatever, וכתיב התם ותהי
לו סוכנת. u'chsiv hatam v'sehi lo sochenes. It says there by דוד,
David, right, that she was to him as a סוכנת, sochenes, as
somebody that kept him warm at night. The point is, he never
dared... he never had relations with her, I know. What can I
tell you? אלא, Ella, anyway, the point is that his donkey was
smarter than him. So you know how God thinks, you can't even
win a fight with your donkey. אלא מאי ויודע דעת עליון, Ella
mai v'yodea da'as elyon, so what did he mean by that? שהיה
יודע לכוון אותה שעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא כועס בה. Shehaya yodea l'chaven
osa sha'a shehaKadosh Baruch Hu ko'es bah. He knew the one moment
that God in the day got angry, and if he would have
given his curse during that moment, it would have been effective. והיינו
דאמרי להו נביא לישראל, V'hainu d'amri lehu navi l'Yisrael, that's what the
prophet says to ישראל, Yisrael, עמי זכור נא מה יעץ בלק מלך
מואב. ammi zachor na mah ya'atz Balak melech Moav. Remember what בלק,
Balak, you know, schemed against you ומה ענה אותו בלעם בן בעור
מן השטים עד הגלגל. umah ana oso Bilam ben Be'or min hashittim
ad hagilgal. From Shittim to Gilgal למען דעת צדקות השם, l'maan da'as
tzidkos Hashem, you should know the righteousnesses of God. האי למען דעת
צדקות השם, Hai l'maan da'as tzidkos Hashem, what does that mean? אמר
להן הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, Amar lahen HaKadosh Baruch Hu l'Yisrael, God
says to Israel, דעו נא כמה צדקות עשיתי עמכם, de'u na kama
tzidkos asiti imachem, know how many good deeds I have, how kind
I was to you, שלא כעסתי כל אותן הימים, shelo ka'asti kol
otan hayamim, all those days I made a point of not getting
angry so Bilam should not have an opening to curse you. Okay,
and that's from Shittim to Gilgal, from the time of, right, well,
yeah,
even though the best of God in some way, God didn't really
want to do it.
Right, I understand that's there is a theme, right, like a days
and times which are, you know, bad things happen and good things
happen we had before, like there's aspects of how the universe works.
That, you know, because we have to still deal with the fact,
look, in the way the story reads, it's almost like Bilam becomes
like almost like a comical figure. Right, so you have to have
to sort of explain it, right, like a you know, in a
way in which he has some power, right? So, all right, anyway.
So, okay. So anyway, that's that's מן השטים עד הגלגל, min HaShittim
ad haGilgal, right, from the sin of Shittim until they got to
Gilgal, the entire period I made sure never to get angry. Okay.
בימי בלעם הרשע, Bimei Bilam ha-rasha, שלא כעסתי כל אותן הימים, shelo
ka'asti kol otan hayamim, had I had shown any anger during that
period of time, לא נשתייר משונאיהם של ישראל שריד ופליט, lo nishtayer
mishoneihem shel Yisrael sarid u'palit, nothing would have been left of the
Jewish people. היינו דקאמר ליה בלעם לבלק, Haino d'ka'amar leh Bilam l'Balak,
that's what Bilam said to Balak, מה אקב לא קבה אל, mah
ekov lo kaboh E-l, what should I curse what God has not
cursed? ומה זעם לא זעם השם, u'mah za'am lo za'am Hashem, מלמד,
melamed, it teaches you שכל אותן הימים לא זעם השם, shekol otan
hayamim lo za'am Hashem, that God made sure as God is not
being זועם, zo'em, God is not getting angry, I have no ability
to curse them. Okay.
So אל זועם בכל יום, E-l zo'em b'chol yom, and God gets
angry every day. וכמה זעמו? רגע, v'kama za'amo rega, and that is
it's a moment, a brief moment, but I know how to be
מחוון mechaven to get that moment. But as but nowadays he's not
doing it. שנאמר כי רגע באפו חיים ברצונו. shene'emar ki rega b'apo
chayim birtzono. Okay. אי בעית אימא, I bayis eima,
לך
עמי בא בחדריך, lech ami bo b'chadrecha, גומר, gomer,
go into your room, סגור דלתיך בעדך, sgor d'latecha ba'adecha, close your
doors in front of you, חבי כמעט רגע, chavi k'mat rega, you
know, or is it חבי chavi
or
חקי? chaki? חבי, chavi, I guess, hide for a moment, עד יעבור
זעם. ad ya'avor za'am.
So you see, so there's a זעם za'am that's זועם, zo'em, right,
ומה זעם לא זעם השם, u'ma za'am lo za'am Hashem, so you
have to if that moment of זעם, za'am, you know, that's the
dangerous moment. Okay. אימת רתח? eimas roscha? Now when is that moment
that God gets angry, since Bilam doesn't can't wasn't מחוון mechaven it
but we're going to tell you when it was. So not exactly,
we're going to give you a framework.
No, no, Bilam did
know, just God just didn't get didn't get angry. Okay. אימת רתח?
eimas roscha? בתלת שעי קמייתא, b'tlas sha'ei kammaisa, the first three hours
of the day from 6 to 9 AM, כחיורא דכרבלתא דתרנגולא, k'chivra
de'charbalta de'tarnagolta, when the crown of, is that what it's called the
crown? Comb, the comb of the rooster turns white. כל שעתא ושעתא
נמי חיורא? kol sha'ata v'sha'ata nami chivra? Gemara says what do you
mean, it's always white.
No, no. כל שעתא ושעתא אית בה סרקי סומקי. kol sha'ata v'sha'ata
it bei sarki sumki. During those yes, it's white, but there are
red streaks. ההיא שעתא, hahi sha'ata, and that one moment that is
the moment that God gets angry, לית בה סרקי סומקי, leit bei
sarki sumki, there are no there are no red streaks. Now, there's
a story. ההוא מינא, hahu mina, this I think in Brachos as
well, דהוה בשיבבותיה דרבי יהושע בן לוי, dahava b'shvivusei d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, that was in the neighborhood there was a heretic in the
neighborhood of Rabbi Joshua ben Levi or sectarian, דהוה קמצער ליה, dahava
kamtzar leh, he was giving Rabbi Joshua ben Levi a lot of
anguish. יומא חד נקט תרנגולא, yoma chad nakat tarnagolta,
so Rabbi Joshua ben Levi wanted to get back at him, wanted
to stop him, so he took a he took a rooster, ואסריה
דכרעיה, v'asrei d'karei, and he tied it up on the on his
bedpost, ואותיב, v'osiv, and he sat. He's going to watch, right, when
it was, you know, when that streak was going to when it
was going to turn white. You know what they say, a watched
pot never boils? Okay. So a watched rooster never turns white. אמר
כי מטא ההיא שעתא אלטייה, Amar ki mata hi sha'ata eltei, when
that time came he said when that moment comes, I'll curse this
מין. min. כי מטא ההיא שעתא נימנם, ki mata hi sha'ata nimnem,
when that time came he had dropped off to sleep. אמר שמע
מינה לאו אורח ארעא, amar shma mina lav orach ara, you see
that it is not the
time, you know, it's not appropriate. כתיב גם ענוש לצדיק לא טוב,
ktiv gam anosh l'tzaddik lo tov, punishment for a tzaddik is not
good, which means for me to punish another person, that's not something
I should be doing. אפילו במיני לא איבעי ליה למימר הכי, afilu
b'minney lo ibai leh l'meimar hachi, I shouldn't even be cursing מינים,
minnim, it's not the right thing for me to do. So at
that very moment he fell asleep. It reminds me of like this
whatever this
Kafka's story, The Castle, which is such oh my god anyway, such
a long hard book to read but anyway anyway like he's the
whole time it's like he's trying to find the meaning of like
some secret like it's all a metaphor whatever it's a metaphor obviously
anyway so finally he's like about to find the answer at the
end of the whole book and then he falls asleep. Anyway yeah.
Also
not fully getting it I mean you know I mean you said
it but you know I'm it sounds like you know oh when
God is angry at that time and then you can like get
God it's almost like you know mechanistic. I push a button, I
curse him, then God will have to agree. I mean but if
God doesn't want it, he's not going to do it.
I understand, but it's a general question about in general, right, בחירה
חופשית bechirah chofshis and divine intervention and how much God allows latitude
for people. And how much God is directly controlling and so on.
It's sort of ways in which God has sort of set the
powers of the universe in place and you can plug into them.
Now God can prevent it. God did prevent it. He chose not
to get angry. Okay, but if he had let things operate, then
evil can can succeed. God, it's the balance between עולם כמנהגו נוהג.
Olam Keminhago Noheg. Now we translate עולם כמנהגו נוהג Olam Keminhago Noheg
in very
mechanistic scientific terms. But you could understand it even if you believe
in a whole metaphysics. There's עולם כמנהגו נוהג. Olam Keminhago Noheg. There's
leaving the metaphysics to operate as they normally would, whether it's belief
in magic and other types of things or whatever or God's anger
or propitious times or evil times like תשעה באב, Tisha B'Av, whatever
before, and whether it's deciding to override them. Okay, yeah.
It's just strange such a describing Bilaam as such an unsavory character
and then they choose his blessings to open the דאוונען. davening.
Well, we're going to get there to some degree. So let's keep
on going. Okay.
Okay. תנא משמיה דרבי מאיר, Tana Mishmei De'Rabbi Meir, we taught in
the name of Rabbi Meir, בשעה שהחמה זורחת, B'sha'ah Shehachama Zorechas, so
what is that moment that God gets angry? It's the moment when
the sun is
shining והמלכים מניחים כתריהם על ראשיהם ומשתחווים לחמה Vehamelachim Manichim Kismreihem Al
Rasheihem Umishtachavim Lachama and bow down to the sun. מיד כועס. Miyad
Ko'eis. That's the moment God gets angry. Okay. ויקם בלעם בבוקר ויחבוש
את אתונו, Vayakam Bilaam Baboker Vayachavosh Es Atouno, he saddled his donkey.
תנא משום רבי שמעון בן אלעזר, Tana Mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar,
אהבה מבטלת שורה
של גדולה
Ahavah Mevateles Shurah
Shel Gedolah from Avraham. Exceeding love sort of destroys the line
of proper sort of restraint that's proper for somebody of a position
of greatness. You don't act certain ways. You have your servants act
it or whatever. But if you're because of the love, you might
crossover that line. דכתיב וישכם אברהם בבוקר, Dechsiv Vayashkem Avraham Baboker, Avraham
got up in the
morning. Right, of course that's ironic because isn't that that's by the
עקידה. Akeidah. Right. I mean there's also וישכם אברהם בבוקר אל המקום
אשר עמד שם Vayashkem Avraham Baboker El Hamakon Asher Amad Sham right
when he went to argue by סדום ועמורה, Sdom Ve'Amora, but presumably
this is the עקידה. Akeidah. So here it's בנך אשר אהבת, Bincha
Asher Ahavta, his love of
Yitzchak, but presumably it's also as we're trying to make the point
of his love of God. Okay. So he actually was so eager
to do it that he didn't have his servants do it, he
did it himself. שנאה מבטלת שורה. Sinah Mevateles Shurah. Similarly, hatred gets
people to act out of normal boundaries of accepted behavior. של גדולה,
Shel Gedolah, even of people of stature. מבלעם שנאמר ויקם בלעם בבוקר
ויחבוש את אתונו, Mibilaam Shenemar Vayakam Bilaam Baboker Vayachavosh Es Atouno, he
is binding up his own donkey. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב לעולם
יעסוק אדם בתורה ובמצוות אף על פי שלא לשמה שמתוך שלא לשמה
בא לשמה. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav Le'olam Ya'asok Adam Batorah Uvemitsvos
Af Al Pi Shelo Lishmah Shemitoch Shelo Lishmah Ba Lishmah. You should
do it even for not the right reason because if you do
it for not the right reason, ultimately it leads to the right
reason. שבשכר ארבעים ושתיים קרבנות שהקריב בלק, Shebis'char Arba'im Ushtayim Korbanos Shehikriv
Balak, if
you count Balak did seven אילים eilim and seven whatever, seven פרים
parim and seven אילים, eilim, fourteen times three is forty-two. So by
the merit of that, and he only did it for the purpose
of cursing Israel.
My gosh, how is this a מצווה? mitzvah? When you say it's
a מצווה. mitzvah.
No, he offered a sacrifice to God.
It's עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
No, I think the assumption is that it's to God. Okay. So
ויצא ממנו Veyatsa Mimenu because Bilaam is trying to get God's favor.
It's outside the משכן, Mishkan, it's always חוץ.
chutz. Alright, anyway. So anyway, so he did this, but he he
was offering sacrifices to God, but it's not just a normal שלא
לשמה shelo lishmah tell like because of less than ideal reasons. It's
actually to subvert a divine purpose to actually
to cause a curse on בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. And nevertheless, ויצא
ממנו רות, Veyatsa Mimenu Rus, Ruth came out of it. Okay. He
merited that Ruth came out of it, which is by the way
an interesting in terms of in terms of the בא לשמה. ba
lishmah. Normally the בא לשמה ba lishmah we mean you start adopting
certain behaviors and then you start doing the behaviors and you realize
the intrinsic value of them and you don't do them for exterior
motivations. But here he did things and never led to him doing
anything good, but somehow the merit of that led to him, like
he got merit for the
deed. And that merit somehow brought about a future generation. So it's
more of that getting rewarded and the good that comes out of
the reward rather than it's like a funny, it's not the normal
way I think we understand. Anyway, אמר רבי יוסי בר חוניא רות
בתו של עגלון בן בנו של בלק מלך מואב, Amar Rabbi Yosi
Bar Chuna Rus Bitoh Shel Aglon Ben Beno Shel Balak Melech Moav,
Ruth was the daughter
of
Eglon, the grandson of
Balak.
היתה. Haysa. אמר ליה רבא לרבה בר מרי, Amar Lei Rava Le'Rabba
Bar Mari, כתיב ייטב אלהים את
שם שלמה משמך ויגדל כסאו מכסאך.
Ksiv Yeteiv Elokim
Es
Shem Shlomo Mishemcha Viyagadel Kiso Mikisecha.
Now
this seems completely irrelevant here. It's when this גמרא Gemara appears somewhere
else, there's a linking אגדה aggadah that links this to the previous
one. Anyway, here it's like a complete parenthetical statement. Said Rava to
Rabba Bar Mari, it says God to, so this is what people
said to David when he anointed Shlomo as his king successor. They
said God should do good, should bring good to the name of
Shlomo greater than your name, ויגדל כסאו מכסאך, Viyagadel Kiso Mikisecha, and
make
his throne greater than yours. So the גמרא Gemara says אורח ארעא
למימרא ליה למלכא הכי? Orach ara lemeimrei lei lemalca hachi?
Is that acceptable to say to a king, your son should be
greater than you? So אמר ליה, Amar lei, no. When it says
משמך, Mishimcha,
it means מעין קאמר ליה. Me'ein kamre lei. May his name be
good משמך Mishimcha from your name, not greater than your name, deriving
some of the greatness. Let his name, you know, have some of
that greatness of your name. דאי לא תימא הכי, De'ilo teima hachi,
תבורך מנשים יעל, Tivorach minashim Yael,
יעל Yael should be blessed among the women. אשת חבר הקיני מנשים
באוהל תבורך, Eshet Chever HaKeini minashim baohel tivorach,
from the women of the tent she should be blessed. So נשים
באוהל מאן נינהו, Nashim baohel mani ninhu, who are the women of
the tent? שרה רבקה רחל ולאה, Sarah Rivka Rachel v'Leah, right? Because
all those stories about them in the tent. So אורח ארעא למימרא
הכי? Orach ara lemeimra hachi? Would could you say such a thing?
That יעל Yael is blessed greater than שרה רבקה רחל ולאה? Sarah
Rivka Rachel v'Leah? אלא מעין קאמר, Ella me'ein kamre,
she should be blessed from the women of the tent. Her blessing
should be somewhat similar to that. Okay, הכא נמי מעין קאמר. Hacha
nami me'ein kamre. ופליגי דרבי יוסי בר חנינא, Upaligi d'Rabbi Yose bar
Chanina, and that argued in רבי יוסי בר חנינא Rabbi Yose bar
Chanina דאמר רבי יוסי בר חנינא, D'amar Rabbi Yose bar Chanina, בכל
אדם מתקנא חוץ מבנו ותלמידו. Bechol adam mitkanei chutz mibno vetalmido. People
are jealous of anybody except their son and their student. That's debatable.
בנו, Beno, משלמה, Mishlomo, from the story of שלמה Shlomo that they
said let his throne be greater than yours and that was a
good thing. I mean there are many people that feel that way,
right? I think that's probably natural like you want your kids to
succeed even more than you. I don't think it's true about everybody,
but anyway, but in general right people are not jealous they דווקא
Davka want their kids to be more successful than they are. ותלמידו,
Vetalmido, I think by student it's debatable, right? You have a professor
he has a great student or whatever, he doesn't want that student
to be have more more popular or whatever or have you know
had a student win the Nobel Peace Prize, that's fine by me!
Oh anyway, איבעית אימא Ibayis eima that says ויהי נא פי שנים
ברוחך אלי, Vehi na pishayim beruchacha elai, by אלישע ואליהו Elisha v'Eliyahu
it'll be double of you know your spirit on me. ואיבעית אימא
Veibayis eima ויסמוך את ידיו עליו ויצוהו, Vaysmoch et yadav alav vayetzavehu,
משה ויהושע, Moshe v'Yehoshua, he put both his hands even though God
only said one of his hands. Okay, so I guess we will
oh you know let's go two more minutes. וישם דבר בפי בלעם,
Vayasem davar befi Bilam, and he put a word a matter in
the word in the mouth of בלעם. Bilam. רבי אלעזר אומר מלאך,
Rabbi Elazar omer malach, God sent an angel with בלעם Bilam to
make sure that בלעם Bilam said the right thing and didn't curse
them. רבי יוחנן אומר, Rabbi Yochanan omer, רבי יונתן אומר חכתא, Rabbi
Yonatan omer chitah, or חכא? Chakei? How do you? חכתא? Chitah?
A hook? He like put a hook in בלעם's Bilam mouth, a
bit or yeah bit or right. And like he dragged בלעם Bilam
like he could totally like had you know he controlled
בלעם's Bilam mouth.
Okay and we'll pick up with here tomorrow, we'll see about all
the blessings of בלעם Bilam and how because God was controlling בלעם's
Bilam mouth, all of these blessings indicate how בלעם Bilam really wanted
to curse and God you know transformed the curse into a blessing,
which is what the פסוקים Pesukim say. So we will pick up
with this tomorrow.
So Rabbi I mean you're saying that this is
זכות? Zechut?